<!-- Copyright (c) 2000, NewsEdge Corp., MakeFeed 3.1.2 11-April-2000 -->

<nitf>

  <head>
      <meta name="PTIME" content="000000"/>
      <meta name="DS" content="PR Newswire"/>
      <meta name="WORDCOUNT" content="976"/>
      <meta name="LOADDATE" content="07/25/2000"/>
      <meta name="PUBDATE" content="07/25/2000"/>
      <tobject tobject.type="news"/>
    <docdata>
      <NE-id storyid="p1109082.704"/>
      <NE-datereceived norm="1998-11-09T00:00:00Z"/>
      <date.issue norm="1998-11-09T00:00:00Z"/>
      <doc.copyright year="1998" holder="PR Newswire"/>
      <urgency ed-urg="5"/>
      <ed-msg info="Converted by MakeFeed 3.1.2"/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdate date.publication="1998-11-09T00:00:00Z"/>
  </head>

  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Apple Introduces AppleShare IP 6.1 - Macintosh Server Software Suite Optimized For Mac OS 8.5  Delivers Sherlock Server-Side Searches, Fastest Performance Ever, Greater &lt;&gt;</hl1>
        <hl2>Apple Computer, Inc. today introduced AppleShare IP 6.1, the latest version of
the Company&apos;s award-winning Mac OS server software and file server suite.</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block>
  <p>
  CUPERTINO, Calif., Nov. 9 /PRNewswire/ via NewsEdge Corporation -- Apple Computer, Inc. (Nasdaq: AAPL) today introduced AppleShare IP 6.1, the latest version of the Company&apos;s award-winning Mac OS server software and file server suite. AppleShare IP 6.1 is optimized for Mac OS 8.5, Apple&apos;s new, must-have operating system upgrade for the Macintosh, and delivers improved file, print, mail and web services to Macintosh and mixed platform workgroups. New features include data transfer performance on Mac clients that beats Windows NT; the ability to conduct server-side searches using Sherlock, Apple&apos;s innovative new search detective; remote server administration; built-in firewall security; and support for hosting up to 50 websites from one server.
  </p>
  <p>
  &quot;Like Mac OS 8.5, AppleShare IP 6.1 is a must-have upgrade for Macintosh Servers,&quot; said Phil Schiller, Apple&apos;s vice president of worldwide product marketing. &quot;With the integration of Sherlock support and data transfer performance on Mac clients that&apos;s up to three times faster than Windows NT, AppleShare IP 6.1 is our easiest-to-use and most powerful server software ever.&quot;
  </p>
  <p>
  <pre>
   Leading AppleShare IP 6.1 features include:
   * Cross-platform file, print, mail, and web services Extremely fast file
   transfers
   * Searching of server volumes using Sherlock technology Remote server
   administration from any web browser
   * Built-in firewall security
   * Native support for Windows clients through the SMB file-sharing protocol
   * Website multi-hosting -- support up to 50 websites from a single server
   * All services managed through one integrated interface
   * Support for IMAP, SMTP, POP and APOP protocols
   * Remote administration of the message database from any IMAP client
  </pre>
  </p>
  <p>
  Supporting the AFP, FTP, and SMB file transfer protocols, AppleShare IP 6.1 makes information accessible over intranets, the Internet, or AppleTalk networks. The file server can provide the fastest possible server throughput for Macintosh clients, as well as offer high-speed transfers for Windows users. Additionally, the included AppleShare client software for Mac OS-based computers automatically uses the faster TCP/IP protocol when it is available.
  </p>
  <p>
  With AppleShare IP 6.1, clients can conduct content searches of server volumes using Apple&apos;s new Sherlock search technology. Finding files or documents is easy, security is maintained, and users receive search results only for files to which they have been assigned access by the server administrator.
  </p>
  <p>
  AppleShare&apos;s already low cost of ownership is further reduced due to the additional flexibility of built-in remote administration in AppleShare IP 6.1. Now, AppleShare servers may be managed from anywhere and from any client using a web browser. Adding users, changing passwords, or administering jobs in a print queue can now be handled from the network administrator&apos;s desk or over a PPP connection.
  </p>
  <p>
  Although AppleShare has always provided a secure networking environment, content and users are safeguarded more than ever with AppleShare IP 6.1. A built-in firewall allows strict control over which clients may access each network service. Access to services can be allowed or denied based on a range of IP addresses or at the individual client level. AppleShare IP 6.1 can also protect against unauthorized electronic mail through powerful anti-spam controls.
  </p>
  <p>
  Windows 95, 98 and NT clients can share access to the server along with Mac clients to access standard Internet services, such as web, mail and FTP. AppleShare IP 6.1 also provides native file services for Windows clients using the SMB protocol, and Windows clients can print to the AppleShare Print Server using industry-standard LPR printing over TCP/IP.
  </p>
  <p>
  System Requirements
  </p>
  <p>
  AppleShare IP 6.1 requires an Apple Power Macintosh or Macintosh Server with a PowerPC G3, 604e, 604 or 601 processor; Mac OS 8.1 or Mac OS 8.5; a minimum of 48 MB of RAM; and a minimum of 40 MB of available hard disk space. Mac OS 8.5 is required to utilize Sherlock server-side search capabilities and firewall security feature.
  </p>
  <p>
  Pricing &amp; Availability
  </p>
  <p>
  AppleShare IP 6.1 is expected to be available by November 23 from Apple and Apple resellers. Estimated retail pricing is U.S. $499 for a 10-client license, $999 for a 50-client license, and $1499 for an unlimited client license that can support up to 500 simultaneous users. Current AppleShare IP 6.0 customers may download the AppleShare IP 6.1 update free of cost from the AppleShare website (www.apple.com/appleshareip). AppleShare 4.x and AppleShare 5.0.x customers may upgrade to AppleShare IP 6.1 for U.S. $499. AppleShare IP 6.1, combined with the latest 300 or 333 MHz Macintosh Server G3, creates the most powerful and easy-to-use Apple server ever. Macintosh Server G3 customers with AppleShare IP 6.0, may download the AppleShare IP 6.1 update free of cost from the AppleShare website. AppleShare IP 6.1 can be purchased from Apple via the Apple Order Center at 800-293-6617, as well as online from The Apple Store (www.apple.com).
  </p>
  <p>
  Apple Computer, Inc. ignited the personal computer revolution in the 1970s with the Apple II, and reinvented the personal computer in the 1980s with the Macintosh. Apple is now recommitted to its original mission -- to bring the best personal computing products and support to students, educators, designers, scientists, engineers, businesspersons and consumers in over 140 countries around the world.
  </p>
  <p>
  NOTE:  Apple, Appleshare IP, AppleTalk, Mac OS, Macintosh and Power Macintosh are registered trademarks and iMac is a trademark of Apple Computer, Inc. Additional company and product names may be trademarks or registered trademarks of the individual companies and are respectfully acknowledged.
  </p>
  <p>
  SOURCE  Apple Computer, Inc.
  </p>
  <p>
  /CONTACT:  Staci Sheppard, 408-974-8404, or sheppard@apple.com, or Russell Brady, 408-974-6877, or brady2@apple.com, both of Apple Computer, Inc./ /Web site:  <a href="http://www.apple.com/"> http://www.apple.com/</a> (AAPL)
  </p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
    </body.end>
  </body>

  <metadata>
  </metadata>
</nitf>
