<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://www.dom4j.org/faq.xml">
  <body>
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    
    <section title="What is DOM4J?">
      <p><b>DOM4J</b> is an Open Source XML framework for Java.
      <b>DOM4J</b> allows you to read, write, navigate, create and modify 
      XML documents. 
      <b>DOM4J</b> integrates with DOM and SAX and is seamlessly integrated 
      with full XPath support.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="What is the DOM4J license?">
      <p>We use an Apache-style open source license which is one of the least
        restrictive licenses around, you can use DOM4J to create new products
        without them having to be open source.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="How does DOM4J relate to DOM?">
      <p>DOM is a quite large language independent API.
        DOM4J is a simpler, lightweight API which is optimised for the Java 
        platform making extensive use of the Java 2 platform such as the 
        Java 2 collections.
      </p>
      <p>Though DOM4J fully supports the DOM standard allowing both APIs to be 
        used easily together.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="How does DOM4J work with DOM and SAX?">
      <p>You can create DOM4J documents from SAX events or existing DOM trees
        or you can output DOM4J documents to SAX events, DOM trees or XML text.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section title="How does DOM4J handle very large XML documents?">
      <p>DOM4J provides an event based model for processing XML documents.
        Using this event based model allows developers to prune the XML tree
        when parts of the document have been successfully processed avoiding
        having to keep the entire document in memory.
      </p>
      <p>For example, imagine you need to process a very large XML file that is 
        generated externally by some database process and looks something like 
        the following (where N is a very large number).
      </p>
      <pre>
<![CDATA[<ROWSET>
    <ROW id="1">
        ...
    </ROW>
    <ROW id="2">
        ...
    </ROW>
    ...
    <ROW id="N">
        ...
    </ROW>
</ROWSET>]]>     
      </pre>
      <p>In the above we can process each &lt;ROW&gt; at a time, there is no 
        need to keep all of them in memory at once. 
        DOM4J provides a <i>Pruning Mode</i> for this purpose. 
        We can register an event handler for a simple path expression and our
        handler will be called whenever the path is complete.
        So to process each &lt;ROW&gt; individually we can do the following.
      </p>
      <pre>
// enable pruning mode to call me back as each ROW is complete
SAXReader reader = new SAXReader();
reader.setPruningMode( "/ROWSET/ROW", 
    new ElementHandler() {
        public void handle(Element element) {
            // process a ROW element
            Element rowSet = element.getParent();
            Document document = element.getDocument();
            ...
        }
    }
);

Document document = reader.read(url);

// The document will now be complete but all the ROW elements
// will have been pruned.
// We may want to do some final processing now...
      </pre>
    </section>

    <section title="Does DOM4J support the Visitor Pattern?">
      <p>Yes. <b>DOM4J</b> supports the visitor pattern via the 
          <a href="apidocs/org/dom4j/Visitor.html">Visitor</a> interface.
      </p>
      <p>Here is an example.
      </p>
      <pre>
protected void foo(Document doc) {
  
    // lets use the Visitor Pattern to 
    // navigate the document for entities

    Visitor visitor = new VisitorSupport() {
        public void visit(Entity entity) {
            System.out.println( 
                "Entity name: " + entity.getName() 
                + " text: " + entity.getText() 
            );
        }
    };

    doc.accept( visitor );
}
      </pre>
    </section>

    <section title="What features are optional in DOM4J?">
      <p>In <b>DOM4J</b> being able to navigate up a tree towards the parent
        and to be able to change a tree are optional features.
        There are some helper methods to determine if optional features are implemented. 
        Here is some example code to demonstrate these features.
      </p>
      <pre>
protected void foo(Node node) {
  
    // can we do upward navigation?
    if ( ! node.supportsParent() ) {
        throw new UnsupportedOperationException(
          "Cannot navigate upwards to parent"
        );
    }
    Element parent = node.getParent();

    System.out.println( "Node: " + node 
        + " has parent: " + parent 
    );

    if ( parent != null ) {

        // can I modify the parent?
        if ( parent.isReadOnly() ) {
            throw new UnsupportedOperationException(
              "Cannot modify parent as it is read only"
            );
        }

        parent.setAttributeValue( "bar", "modified" );
    }
}
      </pre>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>









