<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document url="http://www.dom4j.org/index.xml">
  <body>
    <title>DOM4J The Flexible XML Framework for Java</title>

    <header>
      <p><b>DOM4J</b> is an open and easy to use, interface-based Java API 
      for navigating and manipulating XML documents.</p>

      <p><b>DOM4J</b> combines the best of DOM, SAX, XPath and the 
      Java 2 platform to provide a flexible and powerful framework integrating 
      XML and Java.</p>

      <p><b>DOM4J</b> extends the Java 2 Collections framework to handle XML 
      documents allowing flexible plug and play implementations and has fully 
      integrated XPath navigation support from anywhere in the model.
      </p>

    </header>

    <section title="Getting Started">
      <p>For a quick overview of DOM4J and how to use it try the reading the
        <a href="guide.html">Quick Start Guide</a> or browsing the
        <a href="faq.html">FAQ</a> or the online 
        <a href="apidocs/index.html">JavaDoc</a>.</p>
        
      <p>You can download the current $VERSION$ release 
        or a nightly build via the <a href="download.html">download page</a>.</p>

      <p>Contributors are welcome to join this project. 
        Once you've browsed the <a href="faq.html">FAQ</a> you could try
        sending an email to one of the mailing lists below or check out the
        <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/dom4j/">project page</a>.</p>

    </section>

    <section title="Mailing Lists">
      <p>For DOM4J users there is an email list at
        <a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/dom4j-user">
          dom4j-user
        </a> 
        where you can share ideas and experiences, ask for help, 
        give us feedback or discuss your requirements.
      </p>

      <p>For geeks and advanced techies there is an email list at 
        <a href="http://lists.sourceforge.net/lists/listinfo/dom4j-dev">
          dom4j-dev
        </a> 
        where you can make requests for new features or changes to the API, 
        discuss alternate implementation strategies, submit patches or just
        talk about any relevant topic of the day.
      </p>        
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
