<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document url="http://www.dom4j.org/todo.xml">
  <body>
    <title>To Do List</title>
    
    <section title="Known problems">    
      <p>The following functions are not yet fully supported in the inbuilt
        XPath engine</p>
      <ul>
        <li>id()</li>
        <li>generate-id()</li>
        <li>format-number()</li>
      </ul>
      <p>The optional DOM implementation is not yet at full DOM compliance</p>
    </section>

    <section title="To Do List">
      <ul>
        <li>Better documentation and user guides
        </li>
        <li>Do detailed performance tests against the other XML object models
        </li>
        <li>Ensure that the optional DOM implementation passes the DOM compliance tests
        </li>
        <li>Build an XML Schema Data Types aware DocumentFactory
        </li>
        <li>Build validators using dom4j API such as:-
          <ul>
            <li><a href="http://www.w3.org/XML/Schema">XML Schema</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://xml.ascc.net/xml/resource/schematron/schematron.html">Schematron</a></li>
            <li><a href="http://www.thaiopensource.com/trex/">TReX</a></li>
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>Implement XSLT engine on top of DOM4J
        </li>
        <li>XML Query implementation on top of DOM4J
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section title="Change History">
        <section title="(soon to be released) 0.2 release">
          <p>There following new features were added:-
          </p>
          <ul>
            <li>Clean integration with XSLT via JAXP / TRaX API.
            </li>
            <li>API modified to avoid clashes with WC3 DOM such that a dual 
                implementation of dom4j and DOM is now possible. An early alpha
                release of a DOM implementation of dom4j is available.
            </li>
            <li>XMLWriter and HTMLWriter rewritten so that they work at either 
                the SAX level or the dom4j level. 
                API much improved and more like Reader and Writer in the JDK.
            </li>
            <li>New sorting method added to Node for easier selections of nodes
              which are sorted via an XPath expression. The following
              code sorts all CUSTOMER elements by their name attributes and 
              removes duplicates:-
              <pre>
Document document 
  = new SAXReader().read( new File( "customers.xml" ) );

List customers 
  = document.selectNodes( "//CUSTOMER", "@name", true );
              </pre>
            </li>
            <li>The getText() and getStringValue() methods of Element now return
              the textual values of CDATA, Entity and Text nodes. 
              The previous version only returned Text node values.
            </li>
            <li>Refactored code and removed XPathEngine, XPathHelper and 
                all the static newXXX() methods in DocumentFactory.
                Added equivalent methods to DocumentHelper and DocumentFactory.
            </li>
          </ul>
          <p>This release also includes full XPath source code.
          </p>
        </section>
        <section title="0.1 release">
          <p>Initial release which comes complete with DOM, JAXP and SAX 
            support and integrated XPath
          </p>
        </section>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>









